Guide to the John P. Hoerr Oral History Collection, 1914-2004 AIS.2007.04
ULS Archives & Special Collections
John P. Hoerr Oral History Collection
1914-2004
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Hoerr, John P.
AIS.2007.04
2 Linear Feet (3 Boxes)
This collection documents the research efforts of John P. Hoerr in his effort to create the book, Harry, Tom and Father Rice published in 2005. John Hoerr's research attempted to unearth the events that occurred during the Red Scare in the United States and those who were prosecuted by the House Un-American Activity Committee. His research efforts have brought together a collection of oral histories (consisting of interviews in their original format on micro cassettes as well as transcriptions), a wide array of news clippings, and various other research forms. These interviews, news clippings, correspondence, union mail, Congressional records, legal proceedings, and writings in this collection help to show what occurred to the three main figures of Hoerr's research during the 1950s.
Biography
John P. Hoerr was born in McKeesport, Pennsylvania in 1930. Hoerr witnessed both post-Depression conditions and post-war prosperity in the mill town of McKeesport. In addition, he also worked in a mill in McKeesport during his time in college at Penn State University. This background familiarized Hoerr with the labor conditions in Pennsylvania. After Hoerr graduated from Penn State University in 1953, he moved on to numerous reporting positions in New Jersey, Michigan, and Pittsburgh. After 1960, Hoerr focused his attention solely on labor reporting until 1991, when he began freelance writing. It was during this time when Hoerr began researching for his book, Harry, Tom, and Father Rice, of which one of the main research topics, Harry Davenport, was his uncle. This book focused on telling the story of how the Red Scare brought these three men, Harry Davenport, Thomas Quinn, and Father Rice, together during the Red Scare.
Harry J. Davenport was born August 22, 1902. Shortly after his birth, his family moved to McKeesport, Pennsylvania. Harry followed his brother around in an advertising company and moved from Johnstown to Buffalo to Utica and then to Seattle. Not much is known of Harry Davenport during these cross country years. However, by 1937, Davenport had joined the Communist Party United States of America in Detroit, Michigan.
In 1949, Davenport ran for a congressional seat for the Democratic Party in a Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania district. John Hoerr draws the connection between Davenport and Thomas (Tom) Quinn during this congressional campaign, as it was the first time they met. Quinn was the United Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers of America (UE) Local 601 chairman, who supported Davenport's campaign from the labor sector. He arranged political support for Davenport's campaign from his labor union. Quinn later commented that Davenport would be far more progressive than the other Democratic representatives. He thought it was very important that Harry was elected, "everybody who knew Harry felt that he would make a difference. He was different" (Hoerr, p. 117).
Davenport was victorious over the Republican nominee, John McDowell. McDowell had previously strong ties to the House Un-American Activity Committee as a chairman in 1948 and Davenport addressed this connection to his liberal voting groups. Once elected, he immediately came out in opposition to the House Un-American Activities Committee and attempted to create a resolution to abolish it. Davenport claimed that the House Un-American Activities Committee had been "directly responsible for either murder or suicide… to blame for broken homes, broken lives, and shattered reputations" (Hoerr, p. 138). Despite his strong feelings against the Committee, Harry's resolution was never brought to a vote.
Harry Davenport was also known for his attacks on bigotry, intolerance and racism. He was considered to be extremely liberal in his practices. He supported the repeal of the Taft-Harley Act, continuation of rent control, public housing for low income people, the expansion of Social Security benefits, the increase of minimum wage, and wished to suppress anti-Semitism. Davenport also wished to dispose of a discriminatory poll tax.
Davenport's downfall came only a year after his election to his congressional post. By 1949 and 1950, Communist accusations had increased tremendously, and despite Davenport's stance on foreign communism, he could not escape the accusation of bringing communism to the domestic front. His Communist ties first surfaced when Tom Quinn of the UE Local 601 was accused of supporting Communism. The UE Local 601 that had elected Davenport to power had also been accused of supporting Communism, thus tying Davenport to the party. It was during this time that Davenport was even faced with voting against Tom Quinn in a trial. By 1950, Davenport had lost his congressional seat and retired to his grandmother's house to live. He began writing a book of his life which he entitled, "Death of a Congressman." It is unknown to John Hoerr when Harry Davenport stopped writing "Death of a Congressman," but Harry left almost no papers behind. Harry J. Davenport died in December 1977.
Thomas (Tom) Quinn was born August 10, 1917, but was orphaned in 1918 after both of his parents died of the flu. He was raised by relatives until age twelve, when effects of the Depression sent him to an orphanage. He soon earned a welding certificate and began welding barges before taking a job at the Jones and Laughlin Steel Mill. It was at this mill in 1937 when Quinn first participated in a strike. He later began working at Westinghouse in East Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, in 1941, where he also became a member of the UE 601. By 1946, Tom Quinn had emerged as a leader of UE Local 601 during a national strike against Westinghouse. In response, he became a staff representative for the district and was in charge of negotiating contracts.
By 1949, UE was denounced as a Communist union along with its leaders and supporters. Since Quinn fell under this branch, he was called forth by the House Un-American Activities Committee to testify on his own behalf. Quinn claimed to assert his constitutional rights by refusing to answer certain questions about himself during this trial, and he was held in contempt of court. UE promised to support Quinn if his trial was taken all the way to the Supreme Court. However, in 1953, Quinn was fired from Westinghouse because he had been an accused Communist. In 1955, Tom Quinn prevailed in the Supreme Court case Quinn v. the United States which proved to be a major victory for civil liberties. But, this case was not the end to Quinn's meetings with the House Un-American Activity Committee. In 1959, he was again brought before the committee to testify. It was here that Quinn disagreed with an undercover FBI agent admitting that he had never seen the man before that day. It is observed that during this trial Tom Quinn brought an end to harassment by the House Un-American Activity Committee.
After his dealings with the House Un-American Activity Committee, Tom Quinn remained involved with labor and the UE. He held the position of field organizer in the UE from 1954 to 1962 in Western Pennsylvania. After this position, Quinn moved on to serve as a business agent for the UE Local 610 where he represented two groups of laborers. In 1974, Quinn joined the Pennsylvania Bureau of Mediation and, in 1979 became director. (Refer to the Papers of Thomas J. Quinn Finding Aid for more information) Tom Quinn died February 11, 2005 at the age of 87.
Charles Owen Rice was born in New York City, New York, on November 21, 1908 to Irish immigrant parents. His mother died in 1912 and his father sent him to live in Ireland with family. He returned in 1920 to find his father remarried and moved to Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, which is where Rice spent his teenage years. Rice graduated from Duquesne University and moved on to Saint Vincent Seminary School, where he was ordained a priest in 1934. Rice wished to use his new position to engage in social reform in the areas of labor and working class issues.
Father Rice immediately took an anti-Communist stance in his labor policies. He often spoke out against Communist practices during his weekly radio addresses. Monsignor Rice is well known for his involvement in the 1949 Local 601 Election. This occurred during Rice's second anti-Communist crusade. Father Rice "pushed" Phil Murray to expel UE from the Congress of Industrialized Organization and wished to replace it with a new union in which he engineered, the International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers (IUE). Rice did not stop there; he continued to collaborate with congressional investigators to begin to accuse union members of communist membership. However, he did not foresee his actions continuing as far as they did and harming as many people, including, Tom Quinn and Harry Davenport. Charles Owen Rice died November 13, 2005 with an ambivalent attitude regarding his accomplishments.
Hoerr died on June 21, 2015.
Scope and Contents Note
The John P. Hoerr Oral History Collection is a documentation of an investigation into the lives of three men: Harry J. Davenport, Tom Quinn, and Monsignor Charles Owen Rice. During the process of Hoerr's research, he exhausted various resources to obtain the information he desired, and this collection greatly reflects his research process. A large portion of the materials collected during his research relate to the period in American history known as the "Red Scare." Hoerr obtained a portion of his information through oral history interviews with either those men involved or men who had worked with them in passing. In an effort to relate the lives of the three listed men to that period in time, Hoerr's research includes a rather large section of materials related to the UE and the IUE and their questionable Communist involvement during that time.
Through his efforts, Hoerr amassed a collection of oral history, newspaper clippings, and an assortment of research notes. The variety of the information in these documents is crucial to retelling the roles of Harry, Tom and Father Rice during the Cold War. Hoerr's research greatly reflects the nature of the time period in the way an individual's life was affected with the accusation of communism.
Arrangement
Series I. Oral History, 2000-2004
Series II. Newspaper Clippings, 1940-1960
Series III. Research Notes, 1914-2004
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Previous Citation
John P. Hoerr Oral History Collection, 1914-2004, AIS.2007.04, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Acquisition Information
Gift of John P. Hoerr in February 2007.
Related Material
Michael P. Weber Papers, 1963-1984, AIS.1988.15, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Charles Owen Rice Papers, 1935-1988, AIS.1976.11, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Records of the United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America Local 601, East Pittsburgh, Pa., 1947-1954, AIS.1967.02, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Thomas J. Quinn Papers, 1947-1992, AIS.1973.09, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Bibliography
Hoerr, John. Harry, Tom, and Father Rice. Pittsburgh: University of Pittsburgh Press, 2005.
United States -- Politics and government -- 1945-1953; Politicians; United States -- Politics and government -- 1953-1961; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Oral histories (Document genres); Interviews; Clippings (Information artifacts); Mailing lists; Photographs; Transcripts; Social action; Politics; Labor; Labor unions -- Organizing -- United States; Priests; Communism; Labor unions and communism -- United States; Cold War; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Un-American Activities; International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers; United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation; United States. Congress. Senate. Judiciary Committee; Quinn, Thomas J.; Rice, Charles Owen; Davenport, Harry James
- Oral History, 2000-2004; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The John P. Hoerr Oral History Collection includes a significant oral history series. Throughout his research, Hoerr conducted interviews with various union members, religious leaders, family members, or others who may have been involved with Harry Davenport, Tom Quinn, or Monsigner Rice. These interviews were conducted between 2000 and 2004 and provided Hoerr with imperative information on the Cold War Era. Some of the most important interviews were conducted with Tom Quinn and Monsignor Rice. These interviews are helpful to portray the true emotion of the time and how sincere the House Un-American Activity Committee acted toward possible Communist infiltration of labor unions. The interviews with Tom Quinn and Monsignor Rice also show where the paths of Davenport, Quinn, and Rice crossed.
  This series includes microcassettes of some interviews. In addition, all interviews have been transcribed by Hoerr, including those that are not available on microcassette. This series is arranged alphabetically. The exception to this alphabetical arrangement is a tape that contains an interview with both James Connolly and Tom Quinn.
  - Interview with Bob McCoy (1 and 2), 2002 (Box 1, Tape 1)
  - Interview with Bob McCoy (3), 2002 (Box 1, Tape 2)
  - Interview with John Connelly (1 and 2), 2000 (Box 1, Tape 3)
  - Interview with John Connelly (3), 2004, Interview with Tom Quinn (part 1), 2000 (Box 1, Tape 4)
  - Interview with Tom Quinn (2 and 3), 2000 (Box 1, Tape 5)
  - Interview with Tom Quinn (4 and 5), 2000 (Box 1, Tape 6)
  - Interview with Tom Quinn (6 and 7), 2000 (Box 1, Tape 7)
  - Interview with Tom Quinn (8 and 9), 2000 (Box 1, Tape 8)
  - Interview with Tom Quinn (10 and 11), 2000 (Box 1, Tape 9)
  - Interview with Tom Quinn (12 and 13), 2000 (Box 1, Tape 10)
  - Interview with Tom Quinn (14 and 15), 2000 (Box 1, Tape 11)
  - Interview with Tom Quinn (16 and 17), 2000 (Box 1, Tape 12)
  - Interview with Tom Quinn (20 and 21), 2002 (Box 1, Tape 13)
  - Interview with Monsignor Charles Owen Rice (1 and 2), 2000 (Box 1, Tape 14)
  - Interview with Alex Steber (1), 2002 (Box 1, Tape 15)
  - Interview with Alex Steber (2), 2002 (Box 1, Tape 16)
  - Interview with John Vento (1 and 2), 2002 (Box 1, Tape 17)
  - Interview with John Vento (3); Interview with Tom Quinn (18), 2002 (Box 1, Tape 18)
  - Release Forms (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Transcription of Interview with John E. Connelly, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Transcription of Interview with Tom Foley, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Transcription of Interview with Tom Kerr, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Transcription of Interview with Jim Knox, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Transcription of Interview with Sam Lemon, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Transcription of Interview Excerpts with Quinn's Family, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Transcription of Interview with Charles and Rochelle Quinn, 2001, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Transcription of Interview with Ron Quinn, 2001, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Transcription of Interview with Steve Quinn, 2000, 2002, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Transcription of Interview with Tom Quinn, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Transcription of Interview with Tom Quinn (phone), 2000 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Transcription of Interview with Tom Quinn regarding the House Un-American Activities Committee, 1949, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Transcription of Interview with Tom Quinn regarding UE Shop Representation and Politics, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Transcription of Interview with Monsignor Charles Owen Rice, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Transcription of Interview with Hyman Richman, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Transcription of Interview with Jill Leeds Rivera, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Transcription of Interview with James Rush, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Transcription of Interview with Henry Salczka (Slonska), 2000 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Transcription of Interview with John Vento, 2002, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Transcription of Interview with Robert C. Whisner, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Transcription of Interview with Edwin Wintermeyer, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1940-1960; II.
  Hoerr collected a large number of newspaper clippings relating to Harry J. Davenport's Congressional career as a representative for a Pittsburgh district (1949-1950). These clippings begin with Davenport campaigning in 1946, but mainly refer to his 1948 campaign and 1949 term. Shortly after Davenport won his Congressional seat, his term abruptly ended when he was accused of being a Communist. The other news clippings mainly deal with Tom Quinn and his own issues with Communist accusations and the coinciding legal proceedings. In addition, Father Rice's involvement with the UE probe is well documented. The newspaper clippings demonstrate a great understanding of the fear of communism at the time and the way it affected the lives of the three men. This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Harry Davenport and United Electric, the Worker, 1940-1950 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - The Gazette, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Campaign, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - McDowell-Davenport Campaign, noted, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - The Gazette, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Campaign, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - The Jewish Criterion, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - The Gazette, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Local 601 UE Election Involving Father Rice, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - UE Probe, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - James Matles as leader of United Electric, 1949-1975 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - McDowell Victory, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - November Election, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - UE versus IUE, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Campaign, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Tom Quinn, 1950-1981 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - House Un-American Activity Committee Hearing, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Harry Davenport and Elections, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Monsignor Rice, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Tom Quinn Legal Proceedings, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Research Notes, 1914-2004; III.
  Hoerr collected various other articles and materials referring to Harry Davenport, Tom Quinn and Father Rice. These research notes refer mainly to the Red Scare/Cold War period. A large portion of Hoerr's research notes reflect the transcriptions of the House Un-American Activity Committee hearings in reference to the three main people involved. His research notes touch on other hearings which were also connected to the Communist man hunt, including motives against the UE. In addition, Hoerr documents Tom Quinn's legal proceedings from his own Communist trial. Hoerr's research notes demonstrate the strength the government developed behind the House Un-American Activity Committee. This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Westinghouse Bridge over Turtle Creek Valley, 1914-1916 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Discharges of M. Darino, Fitzpatrick, Panzino, E. Darino, 1942-1967 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Harry Davenport FBI File, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Allegheny County District 29 Official Election Results, 1946, 1948, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Rodef Shalom Archives, 1946-1960 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Davenport Publicity, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Davenport-McDowell Campaign, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Congressional Record, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - House Un-American Activity Committee Hearing, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - James Matles as Leader of UE, 1949-1975 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - UE versus IUE, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - National Archives Files on the Un-American Activity Committee, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - House Un-American Activity Committee Exposes Communist Party Western Pennsylvania, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Harry Davenport Divorce, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Quinn Legal Proceedings, 1951-1955 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - William Peeler 601 Activist and Leader, 1952, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - United States Senate Judiciary Committee "Subversive Influence in United Electric Radio", 1953 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - House Un-American Activity Committee, Quinn involved and Staber Testifies, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - House Un-American Activity Committee Hearing, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - House Un-American Activity Committee "Butler Hearing", 1963 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Monsignor Rice Interview Transcription with Notes, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - James Matles Interview Transcription, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Tom Quinn Oral History by Ron Shatz, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Miscellaneous Tom Quinn, 1983-2003 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Transcription of Interview with David Lawrence, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Quinn-Hoerr Correspondence, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Computer Printer Notes Created by Hoerr while Researching at the UE/Lab Collection, 2000-2004 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Notes on Research in Communist Party United States Internal Files, 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Book Journal of "Harry, Tom, and Father Rice", 2004 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Miscellaneous Davenport, undated (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Photographs of Harry Davenport used in "Harry, Tom, and Father Rice", undated (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Miscellaneous Dorothy Day, undated (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Miscellaneous Father Rice, undated (Box 3, Folder 75)